
 const questions = [
    {
        question: "What is the product of 2 and 7",
        optionA: "21",
        optionB: "28",
        optionC: "15",
        optionD: "14",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "The sum of (-12) and (5) is",
        optionA: "6",
        optionB: "7",
        optionC: "8",
        optionD: "-7",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "How to express 5.5.5.5 using exponent?",
        optionA: "<p>10<sup>2</sup></p>",
        optionB: "<p>5<sup>4</sup></p>",
        optionC: "<p>5<sup>5</sup></p>",
        optionD: "<p>6<sup>5</sup></p>",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "What is the value of <p>0<sup>10</sup></p>",
        optionA: "0",
        optionB: "10",
        optionC: "1",
        optionD: "2",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "A father is 30 years older than his son, and one year ago he was four times as old as his son. Find the father’s present ages.",
        optionA: "43",
        optionB: "41",
        optionC: "44",
        optionD: "53",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "A perimeter of a square is 20 inches.Find the side length of the square.",
        optionA: "4 inch",
        optionB: "10 inch",
        optionC: "5 inch",
        optionD: "7 inch",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Find the 21st term in the sequence 2, 4, 6, 8 ...",
        optionA: "40",
        optionB: "20",
        optionC: "42",
        optionD: "46",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "A train is travelling 1 kilometer in 1 minute and 20 seconds. If the train continues at this rate, how far will it travel in one hour?",
        optionA: "45 miles",
        optionB: "40 miles",
        optionC: "25 miles",
        optionD: "30 miles",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following accurately translates the expression 3x-8?",
        optionA: "8 more than 3x",
        optionB: "3x increased by 8",
        optionC: "The product of 3x and 8",
        optionD: "8 less than 3x",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "The sum of 6 and twice a number",
        optionA: "6<2x",
        optionB: "6 + 2x",
        optionC: "2x + 6",
        optionD: "2 + 6 = x",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "It is the system used to communicate mathematical ideas and must be concise or showds simplicity",
        optionA: "Numberical Expression",
        optionB: "English Language",
        optionC: "Mathematical Language",
        optionD: "Scientific Terms",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Convert 4/25 into a percent.",
        optionA: "16%",
        optionB: "1.6%",
        optionC: "8%",
        optionD: "3.2%",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },


    {
        question: "Get the sum of (-3) + (-10)",
        optionA: "13",
        optionB: "-13",
        optionC: "7",
        optionD: "-7",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "An arc that comprises half of a circle is called a: ?",
        optionA: "Minor Arc",
        optionB: "Diameter",
        optionC: "Radius",
        optionD: "Semicircle",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which number is represented by the word name fifty point one?",
        optionA: "50.1",
        optionB: "50.01",
        optionC: "5.1",
        optionD: "50.11",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "If a car drives at 60 miles per hour for 4 hours, how far will it go?",
        optionA: "200 miles",
        optionB: "140 miles",
        optionC: "240 miles",
        optionD: "2400 miles",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "What is the conversion factor to convert feet to inches?",
        optionA: "(12 inches / 1 foot)",
        optionB: "(10 inches / 1 foot)",
        optionC: "(1 foot / 12 inches)",
        optionD: "(1 foot / 10 inches)",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Fourtimes a number is sixteen",
        optionA: "8x = 16",
        optionB: "4 + x = 16",
        optionC: "4x = 16",
        optionD: "6 - 3x = 16",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Three more than seven times a number is nine more than five times the number.",
        optionA: "3 + 7x = 5x",
        optionB: "3 - 7x + 5x",
        optionC: "3x = 9 + 5x",
        optionD: "3 + 7x = 9 + 5x",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "The first few Fibonacci numbers are 0, 1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13... These numbers are named after Fibonacci, whose real name is?",
        optionA: "Leonardo da Vinci",
        optionB: "Leonardo da Euler",
        optionC: "Leonardo Dicaprio",
        optionD: "Leonardo da Pisa",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Q is a set of positive integers.",
        optionA: "Q = {1, 3, 5, 7, 9,…}",
        optionB: "Q = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5,…}",
        optionC: "Q = {-1, 2, 3, 4, 5,…}",
        optionD: "Q = {1, 2, 3, 4, -5,…}",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "The sum of two consecutive numbers is 31",
        optionA: "x + (3 + 1) = 31",
        optionB: "x + (x - 1) = 31",
        optionC: "x + (x + 1) = 31",
        optionD: "3x + (x + 1) = 31",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "How many handshakes can be made with 10 people if everyone shakes hands with everybody else exactly once?",
        optionA: "45",
        optionB: "50",
        optionC: "30",
        optionD: "60",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Find the value of 3 + 2 • (8 - 3)",
        optionA: "15",
        optionB: "25",
        optionC: "17",
        optionD: "13",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which is the smallest?",
        optionA: "-1/2",
        optionB: "0",
        optionC: "-1",
        optionD: "0.001",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    }

]


let shuffledQuestions = [] 
function handleQuestions() { 
    
    while (shuffledQuestions.length <= 9) {
        const random = questions[Math.floor(Math.random() * questions.length)]
        if (!shuffledQuestions.includes(random)) {
            shuffledQuestions.push(random)
        }
    }
}


let questionNumber = 1 
let playerScore = 0  
let wrongAttempt = 0 
let indexNumber = 0 


function NextQuestion(index) {
    handleQuestions()
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[index]
    document.getElementById("question-number").innerHTML = questionNumber
    document.getElementById("player-score").innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById("display-question").innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;
    document.getElementById("option-one-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionA;
    document.getElementById("option-two-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionB;
    document.getElementById("option-three-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionC;
    document.getElementById("option-four-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionD;

}


function checkForAnswer() {
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[indexNumber] 
    const currentQuestionAnswer = currentQuestion.correctOption 
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option"); 
    let correctOption = null

    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            //get's correct's radio input with correct answer
            correctOption = option.labels[0].id
        }
    })

    //checking to make sure a radio input has been checked or an option being chosen
    if (options[0].checked === false && options[1].checked === false && options[2].checked === false && options[3].checked == false) {
        document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "flex"
    }

    //checking if checked radio button is same as answer
    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.checked === true && option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            playerScore++ //adding to player's score
            indexNumber++ //adding 1 to index so has to display next question..
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }

        else if (option.checked && option.value !== currentQuestionAnswer) {
            const wrongLabelId = option.labels[0].id
            document.getElementById(wrongLabelId).style.backgroundColor = "red"
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            wrongAttempt++ //adds 1 to wrong attempts 
            indexNumber++
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }
    })
}



//called when the next button is called
function handleNextQuestion() {
    checkForAnswer() //check if player picked right or wrong option
    unCheckRadioButtons()
    //delays next question displaying for a second just for some effects so questions don't rush in on player
    setTimeout(() => {
        if (indexNumber <= 9) {
//displays next question as long as index number isn't greater than 9, remember index number starts from 0, so index 9 is question 10
            NextQuestion(indexNumber)
        }
        else {
            handleEndGame()//ends game if index number greater than 9 meaning we're already at the 10th question
        }
        resetOptionBackground()
    }, 1000);
}

//sets options background back to null after display the right/wrong colors
function resetOptionBackground() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    options.forEach((option) => {
        document.getElementById(option.labels[0].id).style.backgroundColor = ""
    })
}

// unchecking all radio buttons for next question(can be done with map or foreach loop also)
function unCheckRadioButtons() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    for (let i = 0; i < options.length; i++) {
        options[i].checked = false;
    }
}

// function for when all questions being answered
function handleEndGame() {
    let remark = null
    let remarkColor = null

    // condition check for player remark and remark color
    if (playerScore <= 3) {
        remark = "Bad Grades, Keep Practicing."
        remarkColor = "red"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 4 && playerScore < 7) {
        remark = "Average Grades, You can do better."
        remarkColor = "orange"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 7) {
        remark = "Excellent, Keep the good work going."
        remarkColor = "green"
    }
    const playerGrade = (playerScore / 10) * 100

    //data to display to score board
    document.getElementById('remarks').innerHTML = remark
    document.getElementById('remarks').style.color = remarkColor
    document.getElementById('grade-percentage').innerHTML = playerGrade
    document.getElementById('wrong-answers').innerHTML = wrongAttempt
    document.getElementById('right-answers').innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "flex"

}

//closes score modal, resets game and reshuffles questions
function closeScoreModal() {
    questionNumber = 1
    playerScore = 0
    wrongAttempt = 0
    indexNumber = 0
    shuffledQuestions = []
    NextQuestion(indexNumber)
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "none"
}

//function to close warning modal
function closeOptionModal() {
    document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "none"
}